A Health Insurance policy of Rs 10 L...
tailor-made for senior citizens...
whose premium is close to Rs 45,000.
After paying so much, you only get Rs 6,000 per day of room rent limit;
co-pay of 30%...
which means you will have to pay 30% of the medical bill from your end.
There are no better features than restoration, renewal & no claim benefit.
And If you download and read the policy wording,
then you will understand that despite having the Rs 10 lakh policy.
If you undergo a cataract treatment,
you will get a maximum of Rs 25,000 claim.
Cancer treatments such as chemotherapy, radiotherapy,
you will get a maximum claim of Rs 3,50,000.
In all other major surgeries, you will get a maximum of Rs 2,75,000.
There are limits levied on treatments on the next page too.
If you don't have an illness, whose treatment isn't mentioned here.
Then you understand that,
You are not paying Rs 45,000 premium for Rs 10 lakh policy,
you are paying it for Rs 3.5 lakh policy instead.
The sad reality is that our parents or senior citizens,
the ones who suffer from pre existing disease.
Health insurance companies consider such people as high risk individuals.
Sometimes, the companies deny to issue the policy.
If they issue, then they consider a certain disease in 'permanent exclusion'...
by looking at it's severity.
They even apply loading on you based on your pre existing disease...
which means, they increase your premium.
In this video, my target is the exact opposite.
For senior citizens, by keeping the premiums at a lower range.
By not compromising the good features.
By avoiding the bad features.
If you have such a policy, then you must find out.
From this video, you must see how to find the best policy.
If you don't get it, then by doing the least compromise...
how to get to the second best or third best policy.
Hi, I am Money Minded Mandeep.
and this is 'The Ultimate Guide to Finding the Best Health Insurance Policy for 2025'.
For your parents.
You might already know what I am about to tell you.
Hence, I have provided the chapters of the videos in the description below.
Jump to the section directly which you want to know more about.
CHOOSING THE BEST COMPANY
We must know which are the good companies and on what basis?
Firstly we will have a look at the incurred claims ratio.
It means If the company receives Rs 100 from the premium income.
How much claim will the company distribute from the premium that year?
If more than Rs 100 claim is distributed...
that means the company is loss making.
And If it distributes Rs 20-30, it means the company is rejecting a lot of claims...
or there are a lot of hidden terms and conditions in their policy.
Using which, it becomes easier for the company to reject the claims.
So a healthy incurred claims ratio is somewhere around 80%.
If the company earned a premium of Rs 100, they distributed Rs 80 from the claim...
and the company will run their business on the remaining Rs 20.
This is the incurred claims ratio of private & public health insurance companies.
Individually and average of the last three years.
If you look at it carefully,
then National, New India, Oriental, United India...
which are the public insurance companies.
Their incurred claims ratio is quite crazy.
That is 140 or 130, all of these are percentages.
Let's have a look at the next criteria, i.e. the number of complaints per 10,000 claims.
The average of all the companies is 22 complaints per 10,000 claims.
We can have a look at those companies, whose complaint data is below 22.
If we look at the lowest,
then we will get HDFC or ICICI.
Even Bajaj Allianz, Kotak Mahindra are good names.
FAMILY FLOATER V/S INDIVIDUAL PLANS
If you think despite parents, we haven't purchased a policy for ourselves.
So why not purchase everyone's policy at once.
Let's take a floater plan, wherein the entire family will be covered.
You think quite well.
But firstly you need to understand what a floater plan is...
Lets say you are four people.
You and your spouse and your parents.
You have purchased a floater plan and the total cover is Rs 20 lakhs.
Now this Rs 20 lakhs is not per person, it's a shared cover.
If something happens to one family member in a year.
And If Rs 10 lakhs get claimed as part of their hospital expense.
Then either for the remaining three members or for all four members.
In that year, Rs 10 lakhs total will be left.
Your parents have a higher probability of visiting the hospital than you.
So they must have a dedicated insurance cover for themselves.
2. If you club your parents in the same floater plan of yours,
then despite being fit, health and young.
You will pay the premium in accordance to a 60 year old person.
For yourself too.
Because the eldest member in the group.
The premium is set based on the senior person's age and pre-existing disease.
The conclusion is you don't have to involve your parents in one floater policy.
You can take one floater policy for both your parents.
But you also need to pay attention that,
If one parent suffers from multiple diseases or is a heart patient, but...
the other parent is fine for now.
Then you can also separate both of their policies.
So that your overall premium becomes low.
And the one's who requires hospitalization the most in the future,
they must have a good or dedicated cover.
THE DEADLY TRINITY
Which features must be included in senior citizens health insurance policy...
But before that you need to ensure that certain features must definitely not be mentioned.
And this is what I call the 'Deadly Trinity'.
Room rent, Co-pay and Disease wise sub limit.
Firstly I will explain room rent with an example.
Assume you have a room rent limit of Rs 5000 per day.
The hospital you happened to visit,
A room costing Rs 10,000 per day is available, all the others are occupied.
You get admitted for five days.
Your treatment costs Rs 4,50,000.
And your total room rent cost is Rs 50,000.
But as per Rs 5000 per day,
you were only allowed Rs 25,000 as total room rent.
You will think of paying the extra room rent cost of Rs 25,000 by yourself.
And your claim of Rs 4,75,000 will be passed.
It doesn't happen like that.
All your treatment expenses are linked with your room rent limit.
The proportionate deduction is levied on it.
It means your room rent limit was 50% of your actual room rent cost incurred...
then your entire claim will be passed as 50%, i.e. Rs 2,50,000.
You have to pay Rs 2,50,000 from your expense.
The next is co-pay.
This is straightforward 10, 20 or 30%... anything that you commit.
You will have to pay a certain percentage of the medical expense from your end.
Third is the sub limit which is the most dangerous.
If you have purchased a Rs 10 lakh policy.
On the majority diseases or treatments, Rs 3 lakh or Rs 3.5 lakh limit is levied.
It means you can't claim Rs 10 lakhs despite paying premium for it.
And this would be the order to compromise.
Assume that you don't get the policy without the room rent limit.
We can take the room rent policy for once.
How? Because room rent is often linked to your sum insured.
In most policies, 1% is the room rent limit of the base sum insured.
It could be less than 1% and oftentimes without writing it in the percentage.
It is defined by room category.
Single AC Private Room.
And it's written in the fine print that,
The most cheapest and private room is allowed.
If there is 1% of sum insured,
i.e. on Rs 10 lakhs sum insured...
you will get a Rs 10,000 room rent limit per day.
which is fine for most cities.
And you can take a sum insured worth Rs 15 - 20 lakhs...
you can modify your rent room upto Rs 15,000 - 20,000.
The bottom line is... If you increase your sum insured and room rent limit,
then you will compromise.
Co-pay, wherein you have to pay 20% of your bill...
This compromise will be extremely costly.
And disease wise sub limit will become an illogical policy for you.
You are also paying a premium of Rs 10 lakhs.
But you will only be able to claim Rs 3.5 lakhs.
MUST-HAVE FEATURES
Now you understand what are the must have features in a senior citizen's policy.
The first is renewal benefit or no claim bonus.
No claim bonus by definition states...
that If you didn't claim for one year, your sum insured will increase the next year.
It will increase until your base sum insured is doubled.
That means If you have 20% no claim bonus,
then your sum insured will double in five years.
Although you must definitely ask your policy bazaar executive that...
If I claim in the third year...
Will the accumulated no-claim bonus until now...
Now several companies have upgarded no claim bonus,
and have now started claiming it as renewal benefit.
Such an upgrade that even If you claim.
even then you will get the bonus of 20-50% written as per the condition.
And in better policies, this isn't removed even after claiming.
If you get it once, then you can carry forward it lifelong.
The second feature is kind of an additional cover,
For eg: HDFC Ergo, Optima Secure, etc.
You might also get in Aditya Birla's policy.
The amount of cover you take, you get it's double from day one.
The third benefit is restoration...
It means If within a year you have exhausted your base sum insured.
It is restored once, for the same year, for the upcoming claims.
In certain policies, restoration is allowed one time.
Whereas, multiple restorations are allowed in certain policies.
But there are a lot of hidden conditions in it.
I have explained these conditions in...
'The Ultimate Guide to Finding Best Health Insurance Policy' in detail.
For once remember this thing...
If you didn't utilize your entire base sum insured in the first claim.
Let's say your policy is worth Rs 10 lakhs, you claimed Rs 8 lakhs.
And Rs 2 lakhs are remaining in the base sum insured.
The next claim you opt for is Rs 6,00,000.
You will get Rs 2 lakhs, but you will have to pay Rs 4 lakhs from your end.
Because a condition was written in your policy's restoration benefit.
That restoration will be applied when your base sum insured will come to zero.
It has become zero in the second claim.
You can get that in the third claim.
But you had to pay Rs 4 lakhs for the second claim from your end.
But again we are speaking for senior citizens and high risk individuals.
It could be possible that you might not get this better restoration.
But still you need to prioritize to take these features...
because this can increase your base cover to 2x, 3x or even 5x.
Less waiting period for pre existing diseases.
Yes, that's a thing.
You might have to pay additional for that.
But depending on the severity of your parents diseases.
You can pay for that and get some peace of mind.
2. Less waiting period for special or slow growing diseases.
which is of two years.
You can amend them to two years in certain policies, by paying extra money.
After that comes, domiciliary hospitalisation...
which means you can't go to the hospital.
If you don't have a bed in the hospital, then you get yourself treated at home.
You can claim the treatment done at home.
The next feature is pre and post hospitalization expenses.
Before any hospitalization,
you could spend a lot towards medicine, diagnostics, etc.
All those expenses are known as pre-hospitalization.
And after a few weeks or months post surgery,
therapies or medications are continued...
These are called as post hospitalization expenses.
In good policies,
Pre hospitalization spanning 90 days and...
post hospitalization expenses spanning 180 days, i.e. 6 months are covered.
Provided you have proper record of all the expenses with bills, which you will furnish and claim.
Maybe in the case of senior citizens or pre-existing diseases...
In this feature, instead of 90 and 180, you might get 60 and 90.
And some other features such as AYUSH.
i.e. Ayurveda, Yoga and Naturopathy, Unani, Siddha, and Homoeopathy.
Yoga and Naturopathy is the same and then Homoeopathy.
There is a catch in this.
You can only get claims in the government recognized AYUSH institutions.
2. You don't get claim in the day care treatment, in most cases.
you must get admitted.
But mostly these treatments are of day care nature.
Day care means, without getting admitted.
You got yourself treated in the morning and returned by evening.
HOW TO CHOOSE BEST POLICIES?
After knowing all this, it's time to find the best policies and compare them.
The best platform is Policy Bazaar.
Full Disclosure: No brand or company has sponsored this video.
Hence, I can transparently and without any pressure...
I am able to provide this unbiased value to you.
But you can understand that this is impossible to do free of cost.
We not only have salaries to pay, but also have to grow as a company.
So that we work better for you.
Hence by keeping the video unbiased.
I am giving you the Affiliate link of Policy Bazaar in the description and the top comment.
If you find value from our work...
and would like to purchase a Health Insurance or Term Insurance.
So definitely click on the link given below.
Go to Policy Bazaar and compare all the policies...
and finally purchase a policy.
By doing this, you can indirectly support us.
By zero additional cost I meant...
If you go through our link or directly, you will have to pay the same amount.
Maybe If you go through us, you might get a discount in certain cases.
From your indirect support, we will try and ensure that,
That we keep getting such educational content for you in the future.
Now since I am asking you to use Policy Bazaar to buy your policy.
Let me also share how it help you.
At the claim time, you will be speaking to a single person.
It's not like customer care, wherein If you call, a different person will pick up.
Then you end up explain the entire story to him.
He will be able to help you then.
If your call gets disconnected, then a third person will call.
You will be speaking to one relationship manager,
no matter the number of times you call him.
He will ensure to remember you entire case and help you at the soonest possible.
Speaking of help in the case of senior citizens.
A representative of Policy Bazaar will visit your house,
will help you end to end and get your documentation done.
So that you spend time with your family members.
They are doing this in close to 180 cities.
You can ask whether you have this service in your city while opting for the policy.
This is very helpful, maybe you are in a different city.
You can't reach on time to help your parents.
So a Policy Bazaar team member will get them admitted to the hospital...
will get all the formalities done.
3. They have an in house underwriting team.
What happens oftentimes is when you opt for the policy from a random agent.
In the process of selling a policy, he might end up issuing a policy.
For which you were not eligible in the first place.
They might persuade you write a lie in the form...
and your claim might get rejected because of it.
He achieved his target, but the loss was yours.
On the other hand, the in house underwriting team with Policy Bazaar.
They will analyze your entire profile...
and recommend only those plans which can be issued for you.
So once the plan is issued, you won't need to face any issues in the claim process.
But most people ask whether,
What If I don't keep anyone as a middleman.
I directly purchase the plan from the insurance company from their website.
My only advice is, you should definitely not do this.
As an individual, you won't be able to fight with the insurance company.
wherein an aggregator could fight.
Or else a better agent could fight, who has a huge business with that company.
So If you know an agent personally like this,
whom you trust, then you can take it from them.
It's not necessary that you take all the support from one source.
You are supporting us by watching, liking or sharing the video.
But I will tell you something about Policy Bazaar,
They offer several services and will fight with the company on your behalf too.
Besides, you might be surprised that,
If you purchase directly from the insurance company,
then the premium could be similar to what you are getting on Policy Bazaar.
So it doesn't make any sense, that you leave all these services...
and you won't get any other service from the company.
The link to Policy Bazaar is given in the description and top comment.
You click on it.
And you keep investigating as I go along teaching you...
Firstly, the Policy Bazaar homepage will appear.
Once you visit Policy Bazaar's homepage, you must click on Health Insurance.
Let's say I want to buy a policy for my father and my mother.
And I considered their age as 62, so they could be qualified as senior citizens.
Now there is an important step here.
Here you need to mention your city.
And this city needs to be where your parents live...
and where they want to get themselves treated.
Because, there is a zone based policy in most of the premiums.
The premium could be cheaper in tier 2 or tier 3 cities.
Because the medical treatments are also cheaper.
So If you entered your hometown's address.
But your parents live in the city and you claim it in the city.
then either on your policy or claim, 20% - 30% co-pay could be levied.
So don't make this mistake again.
There are zone based premiums in most policies,
but there is no punishment of co-pay.
But they only demand one thing, that your address must be accurate.
And most people's claims get rejected because of an inaccurate address.
If you change the house, then you must update your policy immediately.
So that you pay the premium for the correct zone.
You must mention your medical history in the next step.
Needless to say, If you lie even once.
Then you might face challenges in claiming your parent's policy worth lakhs.
Hence you must mention the entire medical history of your parents.
If you think that you don't mention anyone of the diseases, then it would be ok.
It's definitely not like that.
Because, you also need to submit your doctor's prescription pads.
The content written will prove that you suffered from the disease since beginning.
For now, I am selecting diabetes and high blood pressure,
you select as per your illness.
After that, on the screen, you will be able to view plans of all those companies...
as per the current medical conditions, your parents will get as per their age.
Now at the beginning of the video, I had mentioned how to filter good companies.
As per the incurred claims ratio and complaints data,
I will only talk about HDFC, ICICI and Aditya Birla.
But I wouldn't bother studying Star Health,
Niva Bupa, or Care, etc.
Nothing against them, but currently their complaints data is not that good.
In fact, Star Health is suffering through a lot.
Because a lot of hospitals and doctors are not happy with Star Health.
In fact, there is a Doctor's body in Ahmedabad,
they had banned Star Health.
If you are in Ahmedabad and you have a Star Health policy,
then your cashless claim won't be approved.
Anyway let's move onto HDFC, Aditya Birla and ICICI for now.
Firstly, I will select the desired cover.
Let's say my range is Rs 10 - 24 lakhs.
Now we can quickly compare these three policies.
The first point is room rent limit.
And you might be surprised to know that HDFC and ICICI have room rent limit.
And you might wonder that the decision is already done...
Maybe we want to opt for Adity Birla policy, but it's not as simple.
The room rent limit is in default policy.
But you can get in and add a rider.
With that, you can remove your room rent limit.
After that as I mentioned your focus must be on the base sum insured.
You get the renewal bonus and restoration benefit as well.
Because with these two benefits,
your base sum insured could be double triple or maybe 5x higher.
And good to know that there is a renewal bonus on Rs 1.5 lakhs in HDFC.
This is not a no claim bonus.
Even If you claim, then every year Rs 1.5 lakhs,
i.e. you will get 25% of your base sum insured as your bonus.
It means you will have double cover in the fifth year.
There is no renewal bonus in Aditya Birla.
But you can purchase a rider by paying extra.
And ICICI doesn't have renewal bonus,
whereas no claim bonus is of Rs 2 lakhs, i.e. 20%.
The good thing is If you claim someday,
then your no claim bonus won't reduce.
So If you cross 5 claim free year, then your cover will be doubled here.
And also good to know that in all the three plans, you will get restoration benefit.
If your base sum insured ends,
then it will be restored for the next claim in the same year.
Considering, the condition is not levied on restoration...
Until now, all three policies look similar.
Or is it?
If you look at Aditya Birla's policy,
then along with Rs 10 lakhs base sum insured...
Rs 10 lakhs extra from day one is written.
This is very similar to HDFC Ergo Optima Secure policy.
This is not a restoration.
It means from the first day, you can claim Rs 20 lakhs instead Rs 10 lakhs.
Aditya Birla looks better as per this.
You can compare more points.
Such as cashless hospitals.
You can check good hospitals from your city...
whether they are in your network or not.
Also good to know, that in all these three policies.
There is no co-pay.
Hospitalization at home, i.e. there is domiciliary hospitalisation.
There are ambulance charges.
The waiting period in all three policies are similar.
But we can reduce this by adding additional rider money.
You need to do it then.
When your parents suffer from such a disease, and we think that..
we can't wait for three more years, we need to claim now.
You only need to this in Step 1.
You must compare all three plans in high level.
By now, you will receive a call from the Policy Bazaar's executive.
You must tell them your profile, age, pre-existing diseases, etc.
In fact, let's say 5-10 years, you suffered from cancer...
brain tumor, brain hemorrhage... whatever.
If you mention that to the company.
The company would state that, 'Sir/ Ma'am, we will get a plan issued for you'.
We will consider this disease as 'Permanent exclusion' and issue the plan.
You won't get cover on these particular cancer related treatments.
Or else it could be decided on the severity of the disease.
Let's say you have diabetes, and your HbA1c is quite high, 10 - 15%.
So by looking at that, diabetes could be excluded.
Loading could be levied on your premium or more money could be asked.
The company could also state that,
you will only get a maximum of Rs 10 lakhs sum insured.
You can't purchase more than that.
And the premium would be so high that...
It would seem you've taken a Rs 20-30 lakhs policy.
So If you have such a disease history.
So it makes absolute sense that before doing any further research,
you explain your entire profile to the Policy Bazaar executive.
And let them come back to you with plans that you can get.
And those plans could be different from these three plans.
For example, Aditya Birla has seven more plans.
They can very well say to you, that instead of giving the 'Active 1' plan.
They could give 'Active Care Standard Plan'.
So you will further research about this plan.
I will keep the cover as Rs 10 lakhs.
Firstly, we will go to the 'View all features'.
You will find there is a room rent limit here.
Hence you will have to see whether there is an option to remove the rider or not.
You will get the restoration of Rs 5 lakhs, once a year.
For unrelated illness. It means it's quite limiting.
Firstly, on Rs 10 lakhs policy, there is only Rs 5 lakhs restoration.
There is no 100% restoration.
Secondly, If you are getting hospitalized for the second time.
If you are admitted for the same illness, then you won't get the claim.
i.e. you won't get the restoration benefit.
After that, instead of renewal bonus, there is no claim bonus.
It's written as renewal, but in fact it's no claim bonus.
And you will only receive from Rs 1 - 5 lakhs...
It means you will get this upto 50% of your sum insured.
You will get a co-pay of 20% on this.
You must take this policy, when you don't get anything else...
and this is your only option.
Furthermore, you also need to confirm on call.
Whether there is any sub-limit on this.
This was the worst-case scenario.
When company limits tha plan looking at your diseases.
Now let's look at the normal scenario, in case this doesn't happen.
How to customize the three plans we discussed.
So first let's look at Aditya Birla 1.
Sorry Active 1. Have a look.
The first rider is 'reduction in pre-existing disease waiting period'.
You can reduce this to 1 or 2 years from 3.
Accordingly, you will have to pay an additional premium of Rs 10,000.
The next is super credit.
This is it's renewal bonus.
You will get 100% of your base sum insured, every year.
Upto 500%, i.e. by the 5th year your policy will increase 5 times.
If it was Rs 10 lakhs, then it will become Rs 50 lakhs.
This is a nice feature, which was inbuilt in the previous two policies.
Although, the bonus was not of 100%.
It was 25% and 20%.
Which does give you a decent cover, compared to it's ideal speed.
But you will have to find pay additionally in this.
Then consumables cover.
which is gloves, PPE kit, mask, etc.
It also becomes a significant part of your medical bill.
If you need that coverage, you can opt for a separate rider for that.
And If you have a pre-existing disease,
which you think you might have to visit the hospital in sometime...
and you must have it's coverage.
So there is a chronic care rider.
Which will give you cover from Day 1.
Against declared chronic conditions.
You will tell them cover of which diseases you need...
and it will be levied once they accept.
And If the person has BP, diabetes...
It's consistent and the medications is keeping it stable.
And If you could push your parents to improve your lifestyle a bit.
And If you are fairly certain that we won't claim in the next two - three years.
Then there is no need for you to purchase this rider.
After that discounts,
because there is no room rent limit in this.
But If you want to apply, then we can get a discount on the premium.
You must not take this.
You also have an option of Co-pay.
If you want to opt for co-pay willingly, then you will get a discount on the premium.
You don't have to take it.
You have certain similar features in the ICICI plan.
Just like power booster, which states you will get 100% of sum insured every year.
There is no limit on this.
This means If you bought a Rs 10 lakh policy,
it will become Rs 1 Cr after 10 years.
It will become Rs 2 Cr, after 20 years later.
It will keep going on.
But you need to remember that there is a normal renewal bonus in built of 20%.
So there is no additional need to purchase it, especially when...
You won't be able to claim once it reaches Rs 10-20 crore policy.
Plus this is expensive.
And it's also written in the conditons, that If you remove the rider later,
then all the bonus will be removed which you received in this rider.
So purchase it after thinking carefully.
There are two types of riders for pre-existing and chronic diseases.
Firstly, you can change the waiting period from there to one or two years.
You pay the extra premium accordingly.
And another one is the jumpstart rider.
In this you will get cover against declared chronic conditions.
After a waiting period of 30 days.
These are all the declared conditons mentioned on your screen.
But there are further conditions, which I had explained in the masterclass video.
The bottom line is that either the highly paranoid people...
or people who think they might get hospitalized in a few months.
It's for them and not for others.
As I mentioned, there is a room rent limit in this policy.
To remove that, there is a rider as 'room modifier'...
you need to select 'any room' and then apply.
And you need to simply evaluate the HDFC plan.
If you are getting confused, after evaluating everything,
then I will summarize it for you.
Your priority must be high base sum insured.
Restoration benefit along with that.
In which, there would be no hidden condition.
And renewal bonus or no claim bonus.
So atleast not on day one.
But after two - three years, you will have double triple coverage.
After that, you must check the rider of pre-existing disease.
which reduces the waiting period.
Whether you need to opt for that in your case or not.
There are several other riders.
If you keep adding them, then your premium will become unaffordable.
Hence I am not talking about them.
And they are applied case by case.
QUESTIONS TO ASK ON CALL
Listen carefully now.
There is a Policy Bazaar link given in the description and top comment.
Visit the link and do this exercise yourself.
And once you receive the call of Policy Bazaar executive.
Listen to the questiions that you must ask them.
1. Whether room rent limit is included in the policy.
Listen to what they have to say, for your own sake.
2. Whether co-pay is included or not.
Ask them this too. What's the harm anyway.
This is a must ask question.
3. Whether disease wise sub limit is included in my policy or not.
4. How does the restoration benefit work?
Whether it gets activated on the partial utilisation of the base sum insured.
or whether it gets activated on full utilisation.
You need to understand this.
And whether restoration works in both related and unrelated type of illnesses.
or will you get it on only unrelated illness?
It means If you get hospitalized for the second time in the same year...
for the same illness.
You won't get restoration in most cases.
Ask this too.
If you have domiciliary hospitalisation mentioned in your policy,
and If you need that as a feature.
You must ask it's conditions.
Because every policy has a different condition.
There is one common condition.
If doctor has prescribed that you need to be taken home and admitted.
we will offer cover only then, otherwise we won't.
But sometimes there is another condition written that...
because there was no bed available in the hospital.
You have been brought to the hospital to be admitted.
We will only give you cover then, otherwise we won't.
There is a difficult condition.
SUPER TOP-UP
Now let's say after considering your parents pre-existing disease.
Your premium is extremely high.
You are getting the policy, but loading is very high.
According to the pre-existing disease.
So the second way is...
You reduce your cover, so then your premium is manageable.
And you take a super top up policy.
This is not a rider. This is a standalone individual policy.
There are two kinds of policy -- 1. Top up and 2. Super Top up.
If I explain in simple terms, then ignore the top up.
You must take a super top-up.
The reason is because both policies work in a similar way.
But both have a deductible limit.
Let's say that deductible limit in your case is Rs 10 lakhs.
In both policies, you need to pay Rs 10 lakhs from your end.
or else you need to claim from your base policy.
And the amount above that, you can claim from top up or super top up policy...
The top up policy states that,
Your bill costing around Rs 10 lakhs must come under one particular bill.
It will be activated then, which you can claim.
Assume you have three claims, worth Rs 5 lakhs each.
Then you will take the first two claims from the base policy.
And the third claim of Rs 5 lakhs, you won't be able to take that from top up.
You will have to pay that from your end.
Because it is less than deductible.
Whereas the third Rs 5 lakh claim in super top,
you will be able to do that easily.
Because you have already paid Rs 10 lakhs by combining the previous two bills.
And it gets considered as aggregate deductible basis.
And you will get the claim.
So long story short, you need to take a Super Top up.
And the best thing about Super top up policies is that.
By taking either Rs 40 - 50 lakhs or even Rs 1 Cr super top policy...
you won't have to pay much as much as the base policy.
You get such policies for quite a better rate.
However there are better conditions on it.
Similar to base policy...
which you must ask the policy bazaar executive.
1. Whether there is a room rent limit on super top up policy.
Yes, there is a room rent limit in this too.
Please clarify this with your Policy Bazaar executive.
How much room rent is allowed?
Visualize this for me in monetary terms, so that I can be at peace.
But it's best If there are no room rent limits.
There are super top up policies, wherein there are no room rent limit.
After that, even in super top policies,
there are bonus and no claim bonus.
What is it and how much is it? Ask this.
The next question you need to ask...
whether there is co-pay in this. If there is, then how much?
After that, just like base policy...
There are pre and post hospitalization expenses in super top up policy too.
Ask them how many days they are for?
Lastly, in most super top up policies these days,
There is a 'waiver of deductible'...
which means If you gave premium for five years, continuously.
Your deductible will be waived for now on.
That means, you won't have to cross Rs 10 lakhs.
After knowing all this, super top could become a great option for you.
But one more pro tip which you must always remember...
Purchase the super top policy the same day you purchase the base policy.
Ensure the dates don't differ.
Let's take a basic example.
Let's say you purchased the base policy on 1st April.
And you purchased the super top policy next year 1st January.
So from April to December, you don't have any super top up policy.
You know you won't be able to claim.
But let's say two to four years pass, and all the policies are continuously carried out.
Now presume that you get hospitalized in the month of May.
And your claim amount comes to Rs 20 lakhs, wherein...
you claimed Rs 10 lakhs from base policy and Rs 10 lakhs from super top up.
Because your Rs 10 lakh deductible crossed.
Now for this entire year in the base policy, you don't have any money left.
And your super top policy will also get renewed in December.
So in January, February, March...
If you receive a claim and you have zero left in your base policy.
And you have Rs 50 lakhs in super top, just for the name sake.
But it was recently renewed and you haven't crossed the deductible this year.
So you will have to pay for the first claim from your end.
Despite having both the policies.
So ideally you need to do this planning with the base policy,
so that you apply it together.
Even when you purchase the policy on Policy Bazaar,
wherein you add the riders.
When you scroll, you will get an option to add the super top up.
Before adding them, the questions that I mentioned just now.
You must definitely ask these questions.
As per that, you need to take the company's best super top up policy.
Pro Tip #2
If that great super top up policy is mistakenly of the same company...
whose base policy you are purchasing.
So it will be a best deal for you.
Your entire claim could become cashless.
But unfortunately, the company's base policy you are purchasing.
Instead of purchasing the super top from the same company...
if you purchase it from a different company,
then for super top up, you will have to go for reimbursement in most cases.
There won't be any cashless claim.
You do this when you have the super top up policy is better from another company.
CONCLUSION
The good features such as renewal benefit, no claim bonus,
additional cover, restoration, etc.
If these features are being offered in your profile,
then you need to apply on those policies.
You must ask several questions to your Policy Bazaar executive.
because it's your right to ask questions until you are satisfied.
Plus, it doesn't cost any money, they will tell you for free.
I hope this helps.
Link is in the description. Do check it out.
Thank you so much.